If you want to tell the history of the whole world, a history that does not privilege one part of humanity, you cannot do it through texts alone, because only some of the world has ever had texts, while most of the world, for most of the time, has not.
如果你想讲述整个世界的历史，一部不偏重人类中某一部分的历史，就不能只靠文字记载，因为世界上只有部分地区曾经有过文字，而大部分地区在大部分时间里都没有。
Writing is one of humanity’s later achievements, and until fairly recently even many literate societies recorded their concerns not only in writing but in things.
文字是人类较晚取得的成就之一，而且直到相当晚近的时候，甚至许多有文字的社会也不仅用文字，还用实物来记录他们关心的事情。
Ideally a history would bring together texts and objects, and some chapters of this book are able to do just that, but in many cases we simply can’t.
理想的情况是，一部历史应当把文字记载和实物结合起来，本书有些章节恰好能做到这一点，但在许多情况下，我们根本做不到。
The clearest example of this imbalance between literate and non-literate history is perhaps the first conflict, at Botany Bay, between Captain Cook’s voyage and the Australian Aboriginals.
有文字的历史与无文字的历史之间这种不平衡，最明显的例子或许是库克船长的远航船队与澳大利亚原住民在植物学湾发生的首次冲突。
From the English side, we have scientific reports and the captain’s record of that terrible day.
在英国人一方，我们有科学报告，还有船长对那可怕的一天的记录。
From the Australian side, we have only a wooden shield dropped by a man in flight after his first experience of gunshot.
而在澳大利亚人一方，我们只有一面木盾，那是一名男子第一次遭遇枪火后，在逃跑时丢下的。
If we want to reconstruct what was actually going on that day, the shield must be questioned and interpreted as deeply and strictly as the written reports.
如果我们想还原那天究竟发生了什么，就必须像对待书面报告那样，深入而严谨地审视和解读这面盾牌。
In addition to the problem of miscomprehension from both sides, there are victories accidentally or deliberately twisted, especially when only the victors know how to write.
除了双方相互误解的问题之外，还有一些胜利被有意无意地歪曲了，尤其是在只有胜利者会书写的情况下。
Those who are on the losing side often have only their things to tell their stories.
处于失败一方的人，往往只有自己的物品能讲述他们的故事。
The Caribbean Taino, the Australian Aboriginals, the African people of Benin and the Incas, all of whom appear in this book, can speak to us now of their past achievements most powerfully through the objects they made: a history told through things gives them back a voice.
加勒比地区的泰诺人、澳大利亚原住民、非洲的贝宁人和印加人都出现在本书中，如今，他们能够通过自己制作的实物，最有力地向我们讲述他们过去的成就：通过实物讲述的历史让他们重新发出声音。
When we consider contact between literate and non-literate societies such as these, all our first-hand accounts are necessarily twisted, only one half of a dialogue.
在考察像这样的有文字社会与无文字社会之间的接触时，我们所有的第一手记述都必然是扭曲的，只是一场对话的一半。
If we are to find the other half of that conversation, we have to read not just the texts, but the objects.
如果要找到那场对话的另一半，我们就不仅要解读文字记载，还要解读实物。